Inventory of the Garrett Family Papers 1786-1928
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters, 1825-1928, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Letters, 1900-1909., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:12-13)
    - Mary Johnston, Richmond, [Virginia], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 2 April 1903., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Has been told that her [LG] presence has really pleased the Williamsburg party; writes to thank her again; is suffering from a bad headache; sends her latest photograph and mentions that if she does not want it, she should put it in the fire.
    - Mary Johnston, Richmond, [Virginia], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburgh [sic], Virginia, 22 April 1903., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Thanks her for her kindness that she has shown; explains that Mrs. Page has not been able to come to Richmond, and so her son Mr. Arthur Page accompanies the party of Miss McCormack; thanks her for her readiness to call on Mrs. Page when she reached Williamsburg; mentions the possibility of visiting Williamsburg with Mrs. Page.
    - Mary Johnston, Richmond, [Virginia], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 9 May 1903., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Chastises her for not informing her that she would be in Richmond for a longer time; was upset to find that she was in Richmond for several days; thinks that she treated both her and Coralie [Johnston] quite badly.
    - Margaret Guion Ellis, n.p., to Hattie [Mrs. Van Garrett], n.p., 21 May 1905., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Congratulates her on the birth of her daughter; asks her to write and tell of the baby as soon as she feels well enough; sends congratulations to Van as well.
    - Capt. R.E. Lee, West Point, Virginia, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 7 Mar[ch] 1906., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Has not written to her because he was waiting for the circulars about Old Bruton Church; surmises that they were sent to his nephew, R.E. Lee, Jr., believes that it is important to preserve the old; remembers the good times they spent together; would like to see her again and assures her that when he comes to Williamsburgh [sic], he will accept her invitation to visit.
    - Lottie C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Dr. [J.A.C.] Chandler, n.p., 26 Feb[ruary] 1907., 12 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Asks where he found the authority for claiming that her ancestor Sir George Yeardly "was the son of a merchant sailor, and of humble and obscure birth"; indicates her indignation resulting from this claim; prevails upon his fairness as a historian to publish only the facts; includes excerpts copied from the "Yeardly Genealogy" which she possesses and offers to have him peruse if he would visit her home.
    - Harriet Winder Young, n.p., to Hattie [Mrs. Van Garrett], n.p., 10 March 1907., 4 pages. ALS. Partly illegible. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Shares social news of relatives and mutual friends.
    - Mary Johnston, New York, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburgh [sic], Virginia, 2 April 1907., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Thanks her for her invitation to visit; asks if she may come another time; mentions that she is quite fond of her and Miss Mary; has been in New York for ten days and will remain there another week before she returns home; reports that New York is "very big and bright."
    - James U. Goode, Norfolk, Virginia, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 22 April 1907., 1 page. TLS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Has not forgotten his promise to escort her to the opening of the Jamestown Tercentennial; will meet her at the Virginia Building early Friday morning.
    - Mary Johnston, New York, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburgh [sic], Virginia, 7 October 1907., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Apologizes that she could not be in Williamsburg on the 5th; landed in Boston a week ago after having taken the Mediterranean route from Naples; will do some shopping in New York; has enjoyed her summer but is looking forward to returning home.
    - Mary Johnston, Richmond, [Virginia], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 18 December 1907., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Has put the colored card from Boston that she sent into an album of souvenirs; is very busy with her debutante "daughter" and her coming out this season; relives her youth in the coming-out of her debutante; will publish another story next summer; reports that her eyes are troubling her.
    - William M. Pettis, Washington, D.C., to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 16 Jan[uar]y 1908., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Apologizes for not responding to her Christmas card earlier; describes in great deal what a wonderful, noble, and great gentleman her father was; is thankful for the friendship that her father showed him; looks forward to being with him again after this life; reminisces about Williamsburg and the happy times he spent there in youth; believes that education involves more than book-learning, and declares that "what you get out of people, places, situations, environment means more to the mind than in the formative period"; contemplates moving to St. Louis to be with his son, whose wife died 12-15 years ago and who is lonely now; regrets deeply that he was not able to be there for Cousin Letty's death, and that he was not able "to put her sacred dust away as I had promised her."
    - Two letters written on the same page, 29 June 1909[?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Armistead C. Gordon, Staunton, Virginia, to Mrs. Letitia Tyler Semple, Washington, D.C., 29 June 1909[?]. Informs her that the Board of Visitors of the College of William and Mary "adopted a resolution authorizing the erection of the monument of which you wrote"; reports that a copy of the resolution will be mailed to her by the Secretary. 2 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: Mrs. Letitia Tyler Semple, n.p., to Lottie [Garrett], n.p. 6 July [1909?]. Has received her letter that informed her of the action of the Board of Visitors; has yet to receive the letter from the Secretary; asks who the Secretary is and why he has not done what he has been ordered to do; reports that the work is begun and she will soon send the workers the inscription; asks her to preserve this letter from Mr. Gordon. 1 p. ALS.
    - Hattie [Mrs. Van Garrett], on board the S.S. Wensleydale, to her parents [?], n.p., 19 Aug[ust] 1909., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Has been keeping a diary of her trip that she will share when she returns home; gives details of her journey; hopes her children are behaving.
      This letter was included within the letter listed below; Hattie [Mrs. Van Garrett], on board the S.S. Wensleydale, to Josie [?], n.p., n.d.
    - Hattie [Mrs. Van Garrett], on board the S.S. Wensleydale, to Josie [?], n.p., n.d., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Reports that it is so cold that she is wearing her heavy tan jacket from her trousseau; hopes that her children have not been much trouble; has yet to be seasick, along with Cousin Lottie and Van.
      This letter was included within the above letter; Hattie [Mrs. Van Garrett], on board the S.S. Wensleydale, to her parents [?], n.p., 19 Aug[ust] 1909.
    - Van F. Garrett, London, to Miss Mary Winder Garrett, Black Mountain, North Carolina, 1 Sept[ember] 1909., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Will travel from the port at Savannah, Georgia, by train to Black Mountain on their return journey; thanks her for her sweet letters; reports that he has visited Old Barking Church where they saw the Winder Cenotaph and encloses the inscription, describing the ancestry of John Winder of Grays Inn, buried there in 1699; has seen the original charter for the College of William and Mary.
  - Letters, 1910-1928., 21 items. (Box-folder 1:14-15)
    - Mother [?], n.p., to Mrs. Van Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 26 Feb[ruary] 1910., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Postmarked New Orleans, La. Shares reminisces of her sister, who had not long before passed away; mourns her death; shares information pertaining to the will.
    - David E. Cronin, Phila[delphia, Penn.], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 15 Dec[embe]r 1910., 9 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Encloses a few more excerpts from the book he is writing about the Civil War; asks her note that "the whole purpose of the book is against war (physical combat) as a method of settling any question among civilized people"; mentions that he "was glad to read... of Mr. Carnegie's gift toward settlement of national questions by arbitration."
    - David E. Cronin, Phila[delphia, Penn.], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 Dec[embe]r 1910., 12 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Describes rescuing a Confederate soldier who was laying horribly mutilated in a garret; insisted on visiting the soldier even though he was a Yankee soldier; informs her that he met her father at the bedside of this Confederate soldier; encloses more excerpts of his book on the Civil War; explains that his motivation in writing the book is to represent the War in a non-biased way from a man who was there for the sake of future generations.
    - Van F. Garrett, New York, to Lottie [Garrett], n.p., 16 April [19]11., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Wishes her a happy birthday; hopes she is continuing to improve herself; describes his trip to New York with members of his family.
    - Mary Johnston, The Hague, [Netherlands], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 4 July 1911. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Gives details of her sightseeing in The Hague.
    - Hattie [Garrett], Ridgefield, to Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 8 November 1911., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Reports that the new horse arrived, so they all went for a drive to try him out; is relieved that she goes to visit Van and the children every day while she is away; informs her that Father is looking well and is recovering from his long illness; describes her home there; asks about news of Williamsburg.
    - David E. Cronin, Phila[delphia, Penn.], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 18 March 1912., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Mentions that he has finished illustrating Mr. Widener's book; sends her the address of Albert Rosenthal so she may write to him about the painting she would like appraised; wonders if the painting is the one of Washington; informs her that Mr. W.E. Havemeyer would pay handsomely for this painting; assures her that if she has not sold it by the time Mr. Widener returns to America, that he will show it to Mr. Widener who may wish to purchase it.
    - David E. Cronin, Phila[delphia, Penn.], to Miss [Lottie] Garrett, n.p., 23 March 1912., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Advises her to retain Mr. Rosenthal to appraise a tinted print portrait of Washington to determine its value and whether it is unique; informs her that if she knows the history of the painting on glass of Lady Hester Stanhope it would be more valuable than the Washington portrait regardless of whether it was painted by Sir Joshua Reynolds or not; informs her that the Earl of Rosebery would almost certainly be interested in her portrait of Lady Stanhope; advises her that if she is not satisfied with the appraisal of Mr. Rosenthal, she should write to Dr. Rosenbach.
    - David E. Cronin, Phila[delphia, Penn.], to Miss [Lottie] Garrett, n.p., 3 April 1912., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Has talked to Mr. Henkels and described her portrait of Washington to him; reports that Mr. Henkels believes the portrait to be worth between $800 and $1000 as it is quite rare; describes how to examine the portrait of Lady Stanhope to determine whether it is a stipple engraving varnished and painted onto glass, as Mr. Henkels believes it is; gives information about Mr. Henkels.
    - David E. Cronin, Phila[delphia, Penn.], to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 15 April 1912., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Is glad that she had received the advice of Mr. Henkels in addition to the offer of Dr. Rosenbach for the Washington portrait; advises her to use Mr. Henkels' price as leverage for securing a deal with Dr. Rosenbach; reports that Mr. Henkels is also willing to act as her agent in the sale of the portrait.
    - Van [F. Garrett], Williamsburg, Virginia, to his sisters the Misses Garrett, Dublin, Virginia, 5 Sept[ember] 1913., 16 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Describes his return trip to Williamsburg; reports that everything is nice and green and the crops are quite good; shares news of Williamsburg; informs her that Williamsburg just missed the violent storm that swept up the Atlantic coast on the first.
    - Cary T. Grayson, Washington, to Miss Lottie Garrett, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 16 [April 19]14., 1 page. Telegram. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Regrets that he will not be able to visit this week after all.
    - Cary T. Grayson, Washington, to Miss Lottie Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 13 November 1914., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Could not accept her invitation to visit as his trip to Richmond was quite short; informs her that all of her family are in his thoughts, ever since he left college [William and Mary] in '98; is leaving soon to go to New York with the President [Woodrow Wilson]; reports that the President may make a quiet and informal visit to Williamsburg; has spoken to the President about how good she and her family were to him while he was in college; asks her to keep the possible visit of the President quiet.
    - [?], n.p., to Miss Lottie Garrett, n.p. 2 Feb[ruary] 1915. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Note sent with a box of candy to her.
    - Grandma [?], n.p., to Susanne [?], n.p., 13 May 1915., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Shares news of friends and family.
    - Van [F. Garrett], Williamsburg, Virginia, to his sisters the Misses Garrett, Washington Sanitorium, Takoma Park, Washington, D.C., 24 May 1917., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Informs her that his children are doing well on their examinations; reports that many of the boys at the college have had to leave school, either to enlist or to work on the farms; is glad to hear she has the doctor's permission to leave the sanitorium soon and hopes her recovery is permanent.
    - Mary [Garrett?], Williamsburg, Virginia, to Hattie [Garrett], n.p., 29 August 1918., 12 pages. ALS. Partly illegible. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Describes her trip to England in great detail.
    - Hattie [Garrett], Ridgefield, to Van F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 April 1923., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Reports that a tornado swept through her neighborhood, but her home escaped damage; describes the damage in the surrounding area; will go up to New Orleans in the car; will leave to return to Williamsburg next Saturday night.
    - Van [Garrett], Winston-Salem, N.C., to his father Dr. Van F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 15 June 1928., 1 page. TLS. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Writes to express his pride in his father; thanks him for all he has done for him throughout his life; was very honored when he came to visit; misses his family greatly.
    - Van [F. Garrett], La Grange, Georgia, to Miss Mary Winder Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, August 1928., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Describes his trip south through Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia; expects to reach Louisiana on Wednesday.
    - [?], Baltimore, Maryland, to Hattie [?], n.p., 17 Sept[ember] 1928., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Remembers her and mentions that his "recollection of her [her mother] is one of the most beautiful things in my college life"; explains that she is the only thing that draws him to Williamsburg; asks her to let him know when she is to be in town so that he can see her.
  - Letters, 1910-1928., 36 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - C[omfort L.G. Nottingham], Eastville, Northampton, Virginia, to "auntie" [?], n.p., n.d., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Shares a great deal of family and neighborhood news.
    - C[omfort] L.G. Nottingham, Eastville, Virginia, to "auntie" [?], n.p., n.d., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Reports that Mr. Ware, their new minister from Clarke County, gave his first sermon on Sunday; mentions that although he is 25, he looks no more than 17; informs her that Miss Ida Peed and a Mr. Bayly were married last week, but owing to a confusion with the minister over the time appointed for the wedding, the ceremony did not occur until 3 a.m. that night; shares a great deal of other family news and occurrences in the neighborhood.
    - C[omfort L.G. Nottingham], Eastville, Northampton, Virginia, to "auntie" [?], n.p., n.d., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Reassures her that she is being overly anxious about her [CLGN] state of health; would like to go to the Island for two months; shares news of other family members.
    - C[omfort] L.G. Nottingham, n.p., to "auntie" [?], n.p., n.d., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Has not been able to find anything like Mary's dress; encloses samples of fabric that are $0.25 per yard; describes the fashion in dresses this season; reports that Mrs. Ann Seymour died the night before after an illness of just a few days; hopes that she will come to visit in November before the cold really starts to set in.
    - Mary Johnston, Richmond, Virginia, to Miss [Lottie] Garrett, n.p., n.d., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Informs her that Mrs. Walter H. Page of New York will be at the Colonial Inn in Williamsburg the following Thursday; asks her if she could call upon Mrs. Page while she is there; reports that she has been ill all winter and has just returned from the Bahamas; mentions that Mr. Page is a prominent editor-publisher.
    - C.G. Nicholls, n.p., to Van [F. Garrett], n.p., n.d., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Informs him that he should be thankful that Carra is to marry a Virginian and will live near them; asks him to tell Hattie to send a list of presents; shares news of family and friends.
    - Two letters written on the same page, 5 Oct[ober] n.y., 12 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Carra [?], n.p., to cousin Lottie [Garrett], n.p., 5 Oct[ober] n.y. Grieves for the loss of her [LG] friend Mr. Thompson; begs her to come visit so that she may comfort her; mentions that her husband is off to hold court in Shreveport soon; informs her of the news of other family members. 12 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: Virginia [?], n.p., to cousin Lottie [Garrett], n.p. n.d. Begs her to come visit this winter; sends her love. 1 p. ALS.
    - C[omfort L.G. Nottingham], Baltimore, [Maryland], to "auntie," n.p., 12 Oct[ober] n.y., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Mentions that she forgot to send her a scrap of the material for the dress so she could match scarf, gloves, etc.; asks that Lottie sell the kid gloves for $1.25 for she will send her new ones that will fit; describes the suits she has just sent off to Northampton; shares that Nan is coming to visit on the 24th and will stay for several weeks; describes a torch light procession in Baltimore that was so large that it took an hour to pass by; relates that two men were shot during the procession, one dying instantly and one passing away an hour later.
    - C[omfort] L.G. Nottingham, Hickory Grounds, to "auntie," n.p., 11 Nov[ember] n.y., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Informs her that Maria Savage has returned from Philadelphia and that her cousin Henrietta has come down also, but that Maria and Mr. William Savage have since returned home; shares the news that Maria's visit with her uncle was mysteriously cut short, as she had planned to stay at least until Christmas, if not the entire winter; gives news of many acquaintances, including a local wedding; is excited that her room is finished now, but the house will not be completed this year as the workmen have all been released for the winter; asks that she come visit as there is plenty of space in her room; looks forward to the completion of the house so that Aunt Susan, Uncle Garrett, and the children can come for a visit; sends love to all.
    - [Mary Garrett?], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to Vannie [Garrett], n.p., March n.y., 10 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Shares news of many common acquaintances; tries to put to rest the rumors that Mr. Boyden is now her beau by saying that he is simply filling the place of her brother while he is away shares a great deal of information about neighbors and friends; was sorry to hear of his sickness, but as he is well again now she won't speak of the sad subject.
      Also included: 4 pp. AL. Incomplete.
    - Mary [?], Williamsburg, Virginia, to Miss Sue C. Garrett, Baltimore, Maryland, 3 Oct[ober] n.y., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Postmarked 20 Oct[ober]. Informs her that Nannie was slighted that the last letter they received from her did not include Nannie's name; relates that Mrs. Hansford gave birth to a "little heir to her estate"; begs her to persuade Bayly and Cousin Kate to come visit; informs her that the filling has fallen out of her tooth and that she is very worried about the state of it; refuses to go see the dentist in Williamsburg because he is from the Asylum and she is afraid of him; asks if Van can treat her tooth; shares much information about family and friends.
    - Mary [?], Williamsburg, Virginia, to "Father" [?], n.p., October n.y., 4 ALS.pages. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Is glad that he enjoyed his trip to Tennessee but is eager to see him again; informs him that there will be a meeting in Yorktown next week for preliminary measures for the Centennial of 1880; expects many people will go to the meeting; relates that Dr. Wise has been elected visiting physician for the Asylum with an annual salary of $1200, but will retain his position at the College; shares news of family and friends.
    - Lottie [Garrett], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "auntie" [?], n.p., 7 Dec[ember] n.y., 2 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Apologizes for not writing sooner; explains that she has had no time to do anything since Sue was so anxious to have her suit to wear on Christmas Day; is working hard on Mary's dress to have it ready by Sunday; informs her that Father has gone up to Richmond to see about the state stock; relates that Ma has been quite sick but is now much better.
    - [?], 320 Josephine St., to Cousin Lottie [Garrett], n.p., 31 Oct[ober] n.y., 4 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Sends a photograph of herself to refresh her memory; is excited that she will finally come to visit them; informs her that Carrie is improving and that "the baby looks like a different child"; relates that Mother has been quite ill with a cold but is getting better.
    - [Mary Garrett], n.p., to [?], n.p., n.d. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Mentions that Van will only stay a fortnight; asks that she be informed if there is any change in Aunt Charlotte's condition.
    - "Mother" [?], n.p., to "Puss" [?], n.p., n.d., 4 pages. ALS. Illegible handwriting. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Asks her to thank Van for the invitations to the College [of William and Mary?] finals.
    - "Mother" [?], n.p., to "Puss" [?], n.p., n.d., 2 pages. ALS. Illegible handwriting. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Thanks her for finally sending a letter; shares news of acquaintances.
    - C[omfort] L.G. Nottingham, Baltimore, [Maryland], to "auntie" [?], n.p., 24 August n.y., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)